Henry Robinson Luce Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Henry Robinson Luce Papers 1917-1967 1945-1967
MSS30767
Luce, Henry Robinson, 1898-1967
35,000 items
108 containers plus 2 oversize
45 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Editor, publisher, and philanthropist. Correspondence and memoranda, speeches and writings, financial and property records, reports, printed matter, newspaper clippings, and biographical data relating primarily to Luce's publishing career and his involvement in political, religious, civic, and private organizations.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Baldwin, Raymond E. (Raymond Earl), 1893-1986--Correspondence.; Beaverbrook, Max Aitken, Baron, 1879-1964--Correspondence.; Bowles, Chester, 1901-1986--Correspondence.; Bracken, Brendan, 1901-1958--Correspondence.; Buck, Pearl S. (Pearl Sydenstricker), 1892-1973--Correspondence.; Bullitt, William C. (William Christian), 1891-1967--Correspondence.; Dulles, John Foster, 1888-1959--Correspondence.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969--Correspondence.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973--Correspondence.; Judd, Walter H., 1898-1994--Correspondence.; Kissinger, Henry, 1923-2023--Correspondence.; Lodge, Henry Cabot, Jr., 1902-1985--Correspondence.; Luce, Henry Robinson, 1898-1967.; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982--Correspondence.; Menzies, Robert, 1894-1978--Correspondence.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979--Correspondence.; Selznick, David O., 1902-1965--Correspondence.; Skouras, Spyros Panagiotes, 1893-1971--Correspondence.; Swope, Herbert Bayard, 1882-1958--Correspondence.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951--Correspondence.; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975--Correspondence.; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944--Correspondence.
Organizations
China Institute in America.; Council on Foreign Relations.; Institute of Pacific Relations.; National Presbyterian Church (Washington, D.C.); National Urban League.; Rockefeller Brothers Fund.; United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia.; United China Relief (U.S.); United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Fifty Million Fund.; United Service to China.; Yale Law School.; Yale-in-China Association.
Subjects
Christianity.; Civil rights.; Ecology.; Education.; Endowments.; International law.; Journalism.; Presbyterian Church--Washington (D.C.); Social history.; Social problems.
Places
China--Cultural policy.; China--Politics and government.; China--Social conditions.
Occupations
Editors.; Philanthropists.; Publishers.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Henry Robinson Luce, editor, publisher, and philanthropist, were given to the Library of Congress by his widow, Clare Boothe Luce, in 1971 and 1972. Additional papers were transferred from Yale University in 1980.
Transfers
Photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division and sound recordings have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division, where they are identified as part of these papers.
Related Material
The papers of Clare Boothe Luce, also in the Manuscript Division, include Luce family papers and other material relating to the life and career of her husband, Henry Robinson Luce.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Henry Robinson Luce are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1898, Apr. 3 Born, Shantung Province, China, in Presbyterian mission house
1908 1912 Attended Chefoo School, Chefoo [Yantai], China
1912 1913 Attended St. Alban's School north of London, England
1913 1916 Attended Hotchkiss School, Lakeville, Conn.
1920 B.A., Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1920 1921 Student, Oxford University, Oxford, England
1921 1922 Reporter, Chicago Daily News and Baltimore Sun
1923 Cofounded Time with Briton Hadden Married Lila Holz (divorced 1935)
1930 Founded Fortune
1930 1938 Editor-in-chief, Time Publications
1931 First “March of Time” radio program
1935 First “March of Time” newsreel Married Clare Boothe Brokaw
1936 Founded Life
1938 Editorial director, Time, inc.
1940 Organizer, United China Relief
1944 Initiated Commission on Freedom of the Press
1947 Awarded Order of Auspicious Star (China)
1952 Founded House and Home
1954 Founded Sports Illustrated
1964 Retired from Time/Life
1967, Feb. 28 Died, Phoenix, Ariz.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Henry Robinson Luce (1898-1967) span the years 1917-1967 with the bulk of the material dated 1945-1967. The collection is organized in seven series: Special Correspondence, Business and Social Correspondence, Subject File, Speeches and Writings File, Financial Papers, Miscellany, and an Addition. Although the papers primarily document Luce's work with organizations, they also reflect his other professional and personal concerns as well. As head of the Time-Life-Fortune publishing empire, Luce's concerns touched many aspects of political, social, and cultural history in the United States during the mid-twentieth century. Luce believed that America should serve as a democratic example in the world, and his internationalist perspective is documented throughout the collection, most particularly in files on China and international law.
With three exceptions – deeds from Mepkin plantation in South Carolina dated 1917, army records from 1920, and speeches from 1928 onward – the earliest date of papers is 1933 by which time Luce was already a successful editor and publisher and was beginning to devote more of his time to interests outside Time/Life. There is no material for the earlier years when Luce was beginning his publishing endeavors. From 1933 to1967, there are papers on Luce's households, finances, travels, and his advisory and philanthropic activities, but the bulk of the collection dates after 1945 and relates to activities ancillary to his publishing concerns. Papers relating to Time, inc., were retained by the corporation.
The Henry Luce Papers were received at the Library in approximately twenty major sections, with subdivisions corresponding closely with the administrative structure of Luce's office. Although the integrity of this arrangement has been retained, the present organization of the seven series is a simplification of the original order. A large portion originally consisted of files from Luce's office assistants, or personal assistants, in particular, Edward K. C. (“Kip”) Finch, Russell Bourne, and Emmeline Nollen. There is evidence, too, that Allen Grover and C. D. Jackson, officials of Time/Life, were entrusted with Luce's personal and financial affairs. From these people come numerous memoranda for Luce's attention, drafts of correspondence, and responses to his requests for research on a particular subject. Much of the Luce correspondence in the collection was handled by one of his assistants. There is, however, correspondence composed by Luce himself scattered throughout the collection. Notations in pencil on memoranda or on incoming correspondence were Luce's method of suggesting syntactic improvement or to relay the gist of his own thoughts on a subject.
The Special Correspondence series consists of social notes and generally brief correspondence with enclosures from well-known figures of the century seeking favors or an exchange of ideas. Some of these letters are social notes; others relate to organizations or briefly discuss political issues. A note from President Dwight D. Eisenhower, for example, states that he would like to discuss a specific matter with Luce, but there is no record of the actual discussion. The series also includes substantive correspondence, both personal and business, from individuals such as Raymond E. Baldwin, Baron Max Aitken Beaverbrook, Chester Bowles, Brendan Bracken, Pearl S. Buck, William C. Bullitt, John Foster Dulles, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Lyndon B. Johnson, Walter Judd, Henry Cabot Lodge (1902- ), Henry Kissinger, Archibald MacLeish, Robert G. Menzies, Nelson Rockefeller, David O. Selznick, Spyros P. Skouros, Herbert Bayard Swope, Arthur H. Vandenberg, Thornton Wilder, and Wendell L. Willkie. Copies of Luce's replies are usually absent.
The Business and Social Correspondence series includes invitations and requests to sponsor or serve on committees; attend conferences, dinners, and luncheons; appear on radio and televison; write letters of recommendation or articles; schedule appointments; and contribute money. Articles, books, and other gifts sent to Luce are documented through his thank-you notes.
The Subject File is the largest series in the collection. Focusing on Luce's involvement with national and international organizations as director, trustee, sponsor, patron, chairman, committee member, donor, or contributor, it documents the degree to which Luce participated in the life of a particular organization. By far the largest areas of interest for Luce relate to Chinese cultural, social, and political history, Christianity and philanthropy in the United States, and international law. Papers on the latter are confined to the Subject File, with cross-references to the Speeches and Writings. The papers pertaining to China are also primarily located in the Subject File. These extensive files range from Luce's support for Christian missionary work and educational institutions to war relief campaigns as the Chinese fought to expel Japanese forces during World War II and later as Nationalist forces battled the Communists for control of the country. Additional material located in the Business and Social Correspondence series is filed with miscellaneous correspondence in reference to China. China is also the subject of many speeches in the Speeches and Writings File. Files on Christianity and philanthropy are found in the Subject File under the names of organizations, such as those related to Presbyterians.
Luce's other interests evident in the Subject File include innovative approaches to education discussed in files for Kirkland College, Pro Deo, and Yale Luce Professorship. The Institute for Pacific Relations and Rockefeller Brothers Fund files concern world politics. Ecology is a subject of the Mepkin Plantation papers, Valley Beautiful Citizens Council, and Strip Mining Research files. Civil rights for minorities are represented in the National Urban League material.
The Speeches and Writings File includes speeches dated 1928-1967. Luce's principal subjects are China, religion, philosophy, and international law. Since some of the speeches are handwritten or have first and second drafts, Luce's thoughts and ideology emerge from the texts. Also included in this series is a book manuscript written in 1966 in which Luce recalls three decades of American history and the men of political and economic power whom he knew and consulted. The manuscript complements an earlier publication, “The American Century,” which, though not included among the writings in this series, is the subject of correspondence constituting the Addition. Portions of the unpublished book were incorporated into The Ideas of Henry Luce edited by John K. Jessup and published in 1969. A brief diary, circa1940-1947, details a meeting with Franklin D. Roosevelt; handwritten notes and fragments from this period are of a philosophical nature.
The Financial Papers series includes financial and property records. The Miscellany series includes biographical material, honorary degrees, awards, citations, and files concerning the management of household, office, and personal affairs such as gifts and travel.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in eight series:
Special Correspondence, 1935-1967
Business and Social Correspondence, 1933-1967
Subject File, 1933-1967
Speeches and Writings File, 1928-1967
Financial Papers, 1917-1967
Miscellany, 1920-1967
Addition, 1941
Oversize, 1945-1960
Container List
- Special Correspondence, 1935-1967 (Box 1-3)
  Correspondence with occasional attachments and related material from friends, acquaintances, and well-known figures of the day.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and chronologically thereunder.
  - Adenauer, Konrad, 1955-1963, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Adler, Mortimer J., 1951-1966
  - Altschul, Frank, 1936-1960
  - Baldwin, Raymond, 1943-1947
  - Baruch, Bernard M., 1942-1952, undated
  - Beaverbrook, Max Aitken, Baron, 1940-1951
  - Bowles, Chester, 1944-1960
  - Bracken, Brendan, 1936-1952
  - Brownell, Herbert, 1945-1948
  - Buccleuch, Mollie, 1956-1961
  - Buchanan, Wiley T., 1963-1964
  - Buck, Pearl S., 1941-1948
  - Buckley, William F., 1965-1967
  - Bullitt, William C., 1938-1952, 1965-1967
  - Bush, Prescott, 1943-1965
  - Chiang, Kai-shek, and Mayling Soong Chiang, 1943-1965
  - Churchill, Winston, 1955-1961
  - Clark, Mark, 1947-1957
  - Clay, Lucius, 1952-1966
  - Cousins, Norman, 1941-1966
  - Dewey, Thomas E., 1937-1958
  - Douglas, William O., 1942-1948, 1962
  - Dulles, John Foster, 1943-1959
  - Edison, Charles, 1944-1961
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1950-1964
  - Goldwater, Barry M., 1962-1965 (Box 2)
  - Graham, Billy, 1953-1962
  - Herter, Christian A., 1943-1952, 1962
  - Holz, Elizabeth, 1944
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1937-1948
  - Hull, Cordell, 1941
  - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1959-1966
  - Johnson, Lyndon B., 1960-1965
  - Judd, Walter H., 1944, 1953-1962
  - Kennedy, John F. and Jacqueline, 1940-1962
  - La Guardia, Fiorello, 1938-1945
  - Lodge, Henry Cabot (1902- ), 1946-1966
  - MacLeish, Archibald, 1938-1949
  - McCloy, John J., 1946-1966
  - Menzies, Robert G., 1957-1964
  - Miscellaneous “A-Z”, 1935-1967 Correspondents include Joseph Alsop; Nancy Witcher Langhorne Astor; Anthony J. Drexel Biddle; Henriette de Bourbon; William A. M. Burden; Anthony Eden, Earl of Avon; Leverett Saltonstall; Kenneth A. Wood; Alexander Woollcott; and Frank Lloyd Wright, (2 folders)
  - Mundt, Karl, 1945
  - Nixon, Richard M., 1952-1960
  - Paley, William S., 1937-1941
  - Rhee, Syngman, 1947-1952
  - Rockefeller, John D. (1874-1960), 1943-1948
  - Rockefeller, John D. (1906- ), 1941-1961
  - Rockefeller, Nelson A., 1940-1966, undated
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1939
  - Roosevelt, Theodore (1887-1944), 1935-1940
  - Selznick, David O., 1935-1965
  - Skouras, Spyros P., 1948-1961
  - Spellman, Francis, 1941-1966
  - Swope, Herbert Bayard, 1935-1957
  - Taft, Robert (1894-1955), 1937-1947 (Box 3)
  - Truman, Harry S., 1945-1964
  - Vandenberg, Arthur H., 1943-1950
  - Wallace, Lew, 1940
  - Watson, Thomas J., 1935-1955
  - Wheeler, W. Reginald, 1950-1959
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1935-1956
  - Willkie, Wendell L., 1940-1944
- Business and Social Correspondence, 1933-1967 (Box 3-20)
  Letters received and copies of letters sent with related material. Generally includes correspondence, invitations, requests, and thank you notes.
  Arranged alphabetically by category of correspondence, and chronologically within category. More personal correspondence is indicated by name of correspondent.
  - Invitations accepted (Box 3)
    - Committee sponsorship and service
      - 1934-1955, (6 folders)
      - 1956-1967, (7 folders) (Box 4)
    - Conferences and meetings, 1958-1966 (Box 5)
    - Dinners and luncheons, 1960-1966, (2 folders)
    - Miscellaneous, 1949-1966
    - Radio and television appearances, 1959-1966
  - Letters of recommendation, 1947-1967
  - Miscellaneous correspondence
    - Chronological file
      - 1936-1942 Correspondents include Reginald N. Wheeler and Jay N. Whipple
      - 1943-1947 Correspondents include Edward S. K. Hotung, Norman M. Littell, Robert Payne, and Roscoe Pound
      - 1948 (Box 6)
      - 1949-1951 Correspondents include Lila Luce, Elizabeth Stout Davis, and Viant Bliss, (2 folders)
      - 1952-1954
      - 1955 Correspondents include Remsen Bird and Frank W. Boykin
      - 1956
      - 1957-1964, (5 folders) (Box 7)
      - 1965-1967 Correspondents include George R. Reimer
    - In reference to China, 1949-1958, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - No reply, 1947-1948
  - Requests
    - Appointments and interviews
      - 1941-1955, (6 folders)
      - 1956-1967, (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Articles, comments, and opinions
      - 1936-1958, (6 folders)
      - 1959-1967, (4 folders) (Box 10)
    - Autographs, biographies, and photographs, 1954-1967
    - Contributions, refused
      - 1935-1943
      - 1944-1950, (5 folders) (Box 11)
      - 1951, (1 folder) (Box 12)
      - 1952, (3 folders)
      - 1953, (1 folder); (3 folders) (Box 13)
      - 1954, (4 folders)
      - 1955, (4 folders) (Box 14)
      - 1956, (3 folders); (1 folder) (Box 15)
      - 1957-1959, (6 folders)
      - 1960-1965, (7 folders) (Box 16)
      - 1966-1967, (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - Financial assistance, 1940-1967, (3 folders)
    - Miscellaneous
      - 1948-1955, (2 folders)
      - 1956-1967, (5 folders) (Box 18)
    - Political contributions, refused, 1960-1966
  - Thank-you notes
    - Articles
      - 1948-1954
      - 1955-1962 (Box 19)
    - Books, 1948-1965, (4 folders)
    - Gifts
      - Christmas
        - 1948-1956
        - 1958-1967 (Box 20)
      - Miscellaneous, 1948-1967, (2 folders)
    - Pamphlets, 1949-1958
- Subject File, 1933-1967 (Box 20-70)
  Letters sent and received, printed matter, minutes, reports, clippings, memoranda, and miscellaneous attachments.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject and chronologically therein.
  - Aid Refugee Chinese Intellectuals (Box 20)
    - Contributions, 1952-1956
    - Miscellany For additional material see Container 37, Free China Fund
      - 1952, (2 folders)
      - 1953-1959, (2 folders) (Box 21)
  - Air Power League, 1945-1946
  - Air University, Maxwell Air Force Base, Ala., Board of Visitors, 1962-1967, (2 folders)
  - Alfred E. Smith Memorial Foundation, 1948-1966
  - Alpha Delta Phi, 1937-1964
  - American Arbitration Association, 1936-1943, 1948
  - American Asiatic Association, 1945-1948
  - American Assembly, Columbia University, New York, N.Y., 1951
  - American Bar Association See Container 53, Rule of Law
  - American Bureau for Medical Aid to China, 1939-1962 For additional material see Container 37, Free China Fund
  - American Cancer Society, 1945-1964 (Box 22)
  - American Club of Rome, 1953-1955
  - American Committee for Effective Use of the International Court See Container 53, Rule of Law
  - American Committee on United Europe, 1949-1957
  - American Council for the Promotion of Democracy under God See Container 52, Pro Deo
  - American Council on Race Relations, 1945-1946
  - American Friends of the Middle East, 1953-1961
  - American Friends of Vietnam, 1957, 1965 For additional material see Container 40, International Rescue Committee
  - American Fund for Israel See same container, America-Israel Cultural Foundation
  - American Heritage Foundation, 1946-1963, (2 folders)
  - American Institute of Pacific Relations See Container 40, Institute of Pacific Relations
  - American-Israel Cultural Foundation, 1953-1961
  - American-Italy Society, 1951-1960
  - American-Korean Foundation
    - 1952-1954, (2 folders)
    - 1955-1966 (Box 23)
  - American Mothers Committee, 1949
  - American Museum of Immigration, New York, N.Y., 1953-1955
  - American Museum of Natural History, New York, N.Y., 1937-1948, 1962-1966
  - American National Theater and Academy, 1949-1953
  - American Overseas Aid and United Nations Appeal for Children
    - Allocation Committee, 1948, (2 folders)
    - “Campaign Reports,” 1948
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1948
    - Organizing committee, 1947-1948, (2 folders)
    - Printed matter, 1948 (Box 24)
  - American Relief for India, 1943-1945
  - American Society of the French Legion of Honor, 1954-1967
  - American Veterans Committee, 1945-1957
  - American Viewpoint, 1950
  - Asia Foundation, 1955-1956
  - Asia Institute, 1949-1951
  - Associated Boards for Christian Colleges in China See Containers 56-58, United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia
  - Association of American Law Schools, 1965-1966
  - Associazione Italo-Americana See Container 22, American-Italy Society
  - Atlantic Union Committee, 1949
  - Berea College, Berea, Ky., 1951-1966
  - Boston University, Boston, Mass., 1944-1953 For additional material see Container 100, same heading
  - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions
    - General correspondence
      - 1955-1958
      - 1959-1967 (Box 25)
    - Pacem in Terris convocation, 1965
  - Century Association, 1935-1948
  - Chefoo Schools Association, North American Branch, 1937-1966
  - China
    - Art exhibitions
      - Arden Gallery, New York, N.Y., 1939
      - Treasures of the Nationalist government, 1957-1963, (2 folders)
    - Biographical notes and lists of people, circa 1937-1946
    - Chinese students in the United States, 1949-1956
    - Formosa (Taiwan), reports to Luce, 1952 (Box 26)
    - Industrial cooperatives, 1939-1948
    - Japanese war atrocities, 1938
    - Miscellaneous correspondence and memoranda, 1937-1959, (2 folders)
    - Relief agencies, 1933-1940, circa 1953, (2 folders)
  - China-America Council of Commerce and Industry, 1943-1944
  - China Essay Contest, 1940
  - China Institute in America (Box 27)
    - Anniversary dinner, 1951
      - General
      - Speeches and publicity
      - Sponsors
    - China House, New York, N.Y.
      - General, 1945-1960
      - Opening, 1943-1944
    - Chronological file
      - 1939-1944
      - 1945-1951, (6 folders) (Box 28)
      - 1952-1957, (6 folders) (Box 29)
      - 1958-1966, (3 folders) (Box 30)
    - Fund-raising, 1944-1956, (2 folders)
    - Hu Shih Memorial Scholarship, 1960-1963
    - Printed matter, circa 1935-1958
  - China Society of America, 1939-1965, (2 folders)
  - Chinese Refugee Relief, 1962-1963
  - Christ Church Cathedral, Oxford, England, 1961-1964, (3 folders) (Box 31)
  - Christ-Janer, Albert (American hymnbooks), 1955
  - Cima Publishing Co., 1947-1948
  - Citizens Committee on Displaced Persons, 1950
  - Citizens Union, New York, N.Y., 1947-1948
  - Cloud Club, New York, N.Y., 1933-1943, 1959
  - College of Wooster, Wooster, Ohio See Container 64, Wooster, College of
  - College Scholarship Fund for Negro Students See Container 47, National Scholarship Service
  - Columbia Broadcasting System Adult Education, 1937-1942
  - Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
    - Academy of Political Science, 1941-1948
    - General MacArthur Chair in History, 1963
    - Institute of War and Peace Studies, 1950-1954
    - Miscellany, 1950-1962
    - School of International Affairs, 1961-1966
  - Comité International de l'Organization Scientifique See Container 33, Council for International Management (Box 32)
  - Commission on Race and Housing, 1954-1957 For additional material see Containers 24-25, Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions
  - Committee of One Million Against Admission of Communist China to the U.N., 1956-1964
  - Committee on Tax Deductions for Voluntary Giving, 1947-1948
  - Committee to Defend America by Aiding Anti-Communist China, 1949-1950
  - Committee to Strengthen the Frontiers of Freedom, 1959-1960
  - Connecticut Post-War Planning Board, 1943-1945
  - Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs See Container 33, Council of National Defense
  - Council for Democracy, 1940-1942, (2 folders)
  - Council for International Management, 1957-1964 (Box 33)
  - Council of National Defense, 1940-1941
  - Council on Foreign Relations
    - American-Chinese Study Group, 1944
    - China and the U.N. Study Group, 1958-1964
    - Far Eastern Affairs Study Group, 1940-1947